<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mon cahier</title>
    <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mon cahier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 18:43:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>π is rational, or is it?</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 18:43:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/pi/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: π is irrational. Duh doy. We’ve proved it over and over and over again, but this isn’t really about π being rational or not. No no. This is about how mysterious the simplest of technologies tend to be even today when it feels like we’ve mastered technology. But seriously, π ISN’T rational, don’t get any ideas.
The Confusion Try this. Open up your calculator (a physical one) and type in 116 / 13 and look at the solution carefully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The cleverest whisper: The RSA Algorithm.</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/rsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 18:35:38 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/rsa/</guid>
      <description>Known by so many different names, The RSA algorithm, the Asymmetric Encryption or the Public-Private key cryptography is easily one of the pillars that hold the largest network known to us together: the internet. It’s clever. It’s efficient. And it feels seemingly “loophole free”. We’ve all played with Caesar Cipher; Caesar Cipher might just be the simplest example of cryptography (probably the oldest) that we can play with. What’s up with this fancy new stuff then?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hashing Algorithms 101</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/hashing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2021 18:29:54 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/hashing/</guid>
      <description>Cryptography is not a new concept to humans. We have been encrypting messages, trying to make it impossible for other humans to read our messages. It is nothing new. In roman times, Julius Caesar came up with a new kind of encryption where he used to shift all the letters of the message to a certain number. This was called Caesar Cipher. We don’t know if this story is factually correct, but Caesar cipher might be the most known of all the simple encryption techniques.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mathematicians Favourite Pixel Art: Conway’s Game of Life</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/gol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 18:16:10 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/gol/</guid>
      <description>The Game Of Life I created. It was the October of 1970 and the monthly magazine “Scientific American&amp;quot; had a peculiarly interesting article on an apparent game called “life&amp;quot;. That issue of the magazine grew up to be the most sold at the time. The game was The Game of Life by John Horton Conway, an English mathematician. Dr. Conway calls the game a “zero-player&amp;quot; game which accurately describes the amusement you can achieve by just observing the patterns transform from afar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automate The Boring Stuff With Python</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/automationwithpython/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 17:02:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/automationwithpython/</guid>
      <description>Python is powerful. The second most popular language (according to TIOBE rating[27/may/2021]) for a reason (the first most popular language is C for a reason too). Python is convenient for everyone; for beginners, for computer scientists or for mathematicians. All this because of python’s easy usability and the widespread usage. Is python that good? Uh no. Python is a language made on the C programming language. It lets you program the way you want to program: procedural or object-oriented.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NFTs And BlockChains</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/nft/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 16:54:39 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/nft/</guid>
      <description>People are welcoming NFTs as the latest trend in the world of crypto, however we actually had this technology even before the invention of advanced encryption algorithms. Of course, now this technology can be used more effectively and securely, and it might carry the potential to change a lot about the internet you know today. If you don’t have any idea what these new so welcomed additions to the crypto world are, you should.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hidden Services: TOR Network’s real deal</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/tor2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 16:46:06 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/tor2/</guid>
      <description>Hidden services also known as the Dark Web is too cool to exist. As discussed in the last article, the TOR network is a pretty secure network of onion routers. However, we also discussed how if you place yourself at the right places in the network, you can get a lot of information and sometimes even everything. Hidden Services come for the rescue! Servers in the usual system of networks are visible to the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The complexity of Tor: Halloween edition</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/tor1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 20:14:09 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/tor1/</guid>
      <description>We’ve all heard of the deep web or the dark web, haven’t we? The scary network of websites everyone compares with hackers and cyber criminals. We’ve all seen the iceberg picture thing where 90% of the internet is hidden and we only get 10%. We’ve all heard stories of extreme criminality on the deep web. However, tor was meant for you, the normal internet user.
It was the mid-90s and internet was getting popular, really popular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terminals and the art of terminal-ing</title>
      <link>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/terminals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 19:54:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://0jas0jas.github.io/mon-cahier/post/terminals/</guid>
      <description>Terminals. It feels like everyone has heard the word. It also feels like everyone thinks they know what a terminal is, but do they? A terminal’s actual definition has derailed significantly. Here is a terminal:
What? This is not a terminal? You imagined a cool looking dual monitor computer with a black window and a person typing away their life? Nope. This is a terminal. This is actually one of the later iterations of a terminal.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
